This is Wo County Courthouse. Inside are
Rupert Murdoch, four of his children,
and a lot of lawyers. According to the
New York Times, this is the first time
in 2 years they've all been under the
same roof. The Murdochs have turned
against each other, divided into two
factions. And now they're at war.
They're fighting over the family
business, the most powerful media empire
the world has ever seen. If Rupert
Murdoch is not the most powerful media
mogul in the world, he would like very
much to be. Donald J. Trump.
>> Trump is at his best when he's sort of
slightly tongue and cheek like that guy.
He's a very funny guy. These companies
control the news for millions of people.
What they see, read, and hear every day.
Fox News speaks directly to America's
conservative voters and to its current
president. Rupert Murdoch is now 93
years old, and at this point, it's still
not clear who will succeed him.
>> Have your dad ever had this conversation
with you? Someday you'll run this
company.
>> No. No. My father's focused on, you
know, the dayto-day. It's really not an
issue that I concern myself with. As I
said, I
>> other people concern themselves, that's
their business.
>> I've always and will always strive to be
qualified and considered for that
position. It's not my decision.
>> One side wants to seize control of the
family trust. The other wants to stop
them at all costs. Whoever wins will
have enormous political influence, but
their victory will almost certainly tear
the family apart for good.
Fern.
>> Much of our research for this video
draws on reporting from the New York
Times, The Atlantic, and other
accredited news outlets. Direct quotes
attributed to members of the Murdoch
family are largely based on this
reporting. All sources are listed in the
video description. That said, many
details and nuances could not be
independently verified by us. We also
contacted all major Murdoch family
members to request statements confirming
the main aspects of the story, but none
responded.
[Music]
It's early Sunday morning and young
Rupert Murdoch is still in bed. He's 21
now. He's always been a bit of a loner,
but now at Oxford, he's coming out of
his shell. He's socializing and dabbling
in left-wing politics, even joining the
Labor Party. But what he really wants
more than anything is the respect of his
father. Sir Keith Murdoch is an
Australian newspaper man. He dreams of
creating a national news chain in
Australia. So he skillfully cultivates
political influence to bypass media
regulations. So Keith burns with
ambition. He hoped his son would too.
But Rert never did well in school. He
preferred to skip class to go gamble on
horse racing. All his life, Rupert has
yearned for his father's approval, but
now he'll never have the chance to earn
it. I was sleeping in one Sunday morning
when my tutor came in and woke me up,
told me that my father had died. Any
memory I really have of it is one of um
complete shock.
>> Rupert flies back to Australia as fast
as he can, but he misses his father's
funeral. Then he finds out that his
inheritance is significantly diminished.
Sir Keith established family trust back
in the 1930s. Family trusts are commonly
used to manage assets and pass on wealth
to future generations. But Sir Keith's
death is sudden and unexpected, and his
estate carries a serious amount of debt.
To pay this off, Roert's mother had to
sell off half of his father's estate.
Now Rupert is furious. He's been
cheated. Instead of the empire his
father was working to build, he inherits
just a single local newspaper.
The news of Adelaide. He takes it and
does what his father never could. He
builds a newspaper empire.
By the time he's 40, Rupert has gone
further than his father could have
dreamt. He founded the first national
newspaper in Australia, The Australian,
and soon he used that platform to help
catapult a politician into the prime
minister's office. He's conquered
Australia. Next up, the rest of the
world.
[Music]
This is Checkers, the British Prime
Minister's 600 Hector County estate
located 50 km from London. It's
afternoon. Prime Minister Margaret
Thatcher is sitting down to eat.
Thatcher wants to keep this lunch a
secret. For the rest of her life, she'll
deny it ever happened, but notes in her
official archive tell a different story.
Sitting across from her is Rupert
Murdoch. In a few months, Rupert will
turn 50. He's easily one of the most
powerful figures in Australian media.
His company, Newscore, dominates about
twothirds of the newspaper market in the
country, and it's gone global, acquiring
newspapers in the UK and the US. Now, he
sets his sight on a new prize, the Times
of London, one of the oldest and most
respected newspapers in the world.
Acquiring the Times would give him
control over 40% of the British press, a
monopoly, according to UK law. That
would mean legal scrutiny. possibly
hoping to avoid that scrutiny. Rert is
now having lunch with the prime
minister.
Back in Australia, he established a
successful formula. First, acquire a
newspaper and make it successful through
populist journalism. Then, leverage that
success to obtain more properties. Next,
gain control over a prestigious
newspaper. Respected broad sheets tend
to reach a different audience, powerful
people, including politicians. Speaking
directly to people like this means a
chance to influence policy through
endorsements and editorials. It can even
mean having an impact on elections. For
a newspaper mogul intent on growing an
empire, that kind of influence could be
worth its weight in gold. In the UK,
Rupert applied his formula on a bigger
stage. His towhold was News of the
World, a weekly left-wing tabloid
newspaper he acquired in 1969. A year
later, he added a daily, The Sun. Both
papers became known for headlines like
these and for a willingness to focus on
sex, drugs, and scandal. The Sun even
introduced a new daily feature, a
topless page three girl. It broke with
tradition on Fleet Street, home of the
British press. We were tearing up the
old ways and inventing a new form of
journalism, a new way. We were the on
turbula of Fleet Street and proud to be
so.
>> Sales began climbing. A decade later,
The Sun was Britain's bestselling
tabloid. The new approach also earned
Rert a nickname. That strat of society
called him the dirty digger.
[Music]
Now Rupert is making his case to
Thatcher for why he should be allowed to
take over the Times of London. He just
wants to make improvements to the paper.
He says he'll be a hands-off owner.
Later on, he'll guarantee this with a
written promise. Afterward, he thanks
her for the lunch with this handwritten
note. He calls her my dear prime
minister.
There's no evidence that Rupert and
Thatcher made a deal. Thatcher carefully
avoids any suggestion of this, even in
her own documents. Her official record
of the event states she did no more than
wish him well in his bid. But this
official record doesn't even cover the
entire meeting, just the salient points.
And in accordance with Thatcher's
wishes, it was kept confidential. No one
outside of the prime minister's office
was to know about her lunch with Rupert.
This has led some to speculate that over
lunch, Rupert Murdoch and Margaret
Thatcher may have arrived at an
understanding. What is certain is that
within weeks the Monopolies Commission
decides not to look into RER buying the
Times. Soon he owns the paper.
At the same time, Britain is stuck in a
recession. Thatcher is deeply unpopular.
But in April 1982, Britain goes to war
with Argentina over the Faulland
Islands, and Rupert's tabloid, The Sun,
goes all in on supporting it. As
Britain's bestselling tabloid, The Sun
reaches a huge portion of the British
public, and many believe its aggressive
support for the war hugely boosted
Thatcher's popularity. Some have even
suggested this might have saved her
prime ministership.
Rupert applies his formula on the other
side of the Atlantic, too. His tabloid
New York Post helps deliver the longshot
candidate at Cootch to the New York
City's mayor's office.
>> I wouldn't be in a position to say I was
mayor of New York City if Rert hadn't uh
endorsed me. He gave me credit
developing.
>> Then the Post gets behind Ronald
Reagan's presidential candidacy.
>> The endorsement o of the New York Post
of Ronald Reagan was crucial. Reagan
carried New York State in the 1980
election.
>> During the Reagan administration,
Rubert's drive to expand faces fewer
barriers. At the time, American
regulations prohibit owning a major
newspaper and a television station that
share the same market. Under the Reagan
administration, the Federal
Communications Commission temporarily
waved these regulations for Roupert.
Only American citizens can directly own
more than 20% of a TV station. So,
Rupert applies for citizenship. In
September 1986, he receives it quickly
enough that some claim his application
was fasttracked. With these roadblocks
out of the way, he's free to buy a
handful of television stations.
Then, he buys a movie studio, 20th
Century Fox.
[Music]
A month after receiving his American
citizenship, he combines these new
assets and launches the first new major
broadcast television network since the
1950s. Fox's shows are a bright, edgy
alternative to straight lace broadcast
television, and Living Color presents
sketch comedy with a black hip hop
inflected perspective. The Simpsons and
Married with Children reinvent the
family sitcom as dysfunctional and even
racy. And then Reagan eliminates the
fairness doctrine, which had required
broadcasters to give equal time to both
sides of controversial issues. Many see
this as paving the way for partisan
media and eventually a channel that will
change the American media landscape
forever.
[Music]
Thank you very much for your attendance
at such short notice. uh you have the uh
press statement I think which tells you
uh everything and that
>> on January 30th 1996 Rupert Murdoch
announces the Fox News Channel. His
network TV station also called Fox has
been on the air for a decade. Now he's
finally making the leap to cable.
Rupert's news station will be
challenging the 400lb gorilla of 24-hour
news CNN. To pull it off, he hires this
man.
>> I'd like to thank uh Mr. Murdoch for the
kind words. Thank you all for coming
this morning on short notice. I know
that you're good journalists. Therefore,
>> his name is Roger Als. Rupert hired him
to build Fox News from scratch. They
have a lot in common. Conservative
politics, an instinctively
anti-establishment point of view aimed
at what they see as liberal elites. It's
a crystal clear vision for Fox News. The
network will cater to an overlooked
audience, older, white, less educated,
church-going, rural, and most of all,
conservative, so-called middle America.
The two men will reportedly joke that
they've uncovered a whole new market,
half the country. Ills was media adviser
to presidents Richard Nixon, Ronald
Reagan, and George HW Bush. He knows the
target demographic well. He's also a
controversial figure in the media
landscape just weeks before the debut of
the Fox News Channel. He left a job at
NBC after reportedly hurling an
anti-Semitic slur at a coworker. And
he's known as a magician of the divisive
power of media. For Fox, he's later
quoted as saying,
>> "It's not enough that conservatives like
us, but that liberals hate us."
>> Fox News Channel, fair and balanced.
>> When Fox debuts, the studio looks cheap,
thrown together, but it's undeniably
different. It's colorful and
deliberately edgy. Over and over, the
station's slogan is repeated, fair, and
balanced. It worked, and ratings soared.
By 2002, Fox News had become the most
watched cable news channel in America.
For many conservatives, it became the
only channel and its base was always
expanding. In 2007, a study found that
when Fox News entered a local media
market, it pushed viewers to the right
and made them more likely to vote
Republican. This was called the Fox News
effect. If a Republican politician
wanted to reach their base on the
national stage, it was said the only
road went through Fox.
>> Republicans originally thought that Fox
worked for us. Uh, and now we're
discovering we work for Fox. Newscor's
power and influence now spanned several
continents, but Rupert himself was
aging. He had always considered his
empire a family business, and like his
father, he had considered his legacy.
>> My two sons are very interested in
having major careers, and I'm doing what
I can to train them, give them
opportunities, and see what mistakes
they make and what triumphs they have.
>> But which of his children would one day
take control? On that point, Rubert
could be mattlingly hard to read. You
have three adult children, Lachlan,
James, and Elizabeth, each of whom is
now a very accomplished media executive
in his own right. At the same time, you
have reportedly told your biggest
outside shareholder, Prince Wed, quote,
"I'm going to stay on as CEO until I'm
130."
>> So, as
>> I'm more realistic than that, really.
[Music]
>> Rupert Murdoch raises children to be
media moguls. He pushed them to be part
of his empire.
>> We knew that dad loved the time he had
with us and he wanted us to be part of
his world. And I think that as a child
you have to be part of that world in
some ways if you were going to be
engaged with him.
>> One day, one of them would take over the
family business. But which one?
According to observers, the children
were constantly trying to figure out
where they stood with their father. Who
did he favor at any given time? Family
life revolved around succession. Each
child grew up trying to prove themselves
worthy.
Elizabeth Murdoch is often described as
bright, capable, and like her father.
With his help, she purchased a pair of
television stations in California. About
a year later, she sold them for a $12
million profit. Soon, she'll be climbing
the corporate ladder at her father's
satellite TV station, BK SkyB. She's
tough, ambitious, and has her eye on the
top job. I have always and will always
strive to be qualified and considered
for that position. It's not my decision.
>> But in the race for succession, many
believe she has a handicap.
>> It has been said that he's never been a
person particularly comfortable with
women in senior positions.
>> He say you got a quote on that.
>> I haven't got a quote on that. It's been
says I said as I said
>> I think he ever actually said I don't
know if that I don't know if that's
true. Um I can think of a number of
senior women that he's come to count on
and rely on in very very important
positions. I think dad is um
traditional in many ways.
>> Lachlan Murdoch is Rupert's eldest son.
He's often said to be the apple of his
father's eye. He just graduated from
Princeton University. Now he's working
on his father's newspapers in Australia.
He's young, rich, and a budding
celebrity.
>> Have your dad ever had this conversation
with you? Someday you'll run this
company.
>> No. No. My father's focused on, you
know, the day-to-day.
>> Prudence is Rupert's only child from his
first marriage. She's also the only
Murdoch sibling to avoid the family
business, though her husband works for
News Corp. James Murdoch is often called
the family rebel. Dropped out of Harvard
to follow the Grateful Dead on tour.
Founded a hip-hop label Rockus Records.
>> Yeah, that's really not an issue that I
concern myself with. As I said,
>> lots of other people concern themselves.
>> That's their business. Anna Murdoch is
Rupert's second wife. Anna has been part
of NewsCore since she was 18 years old.
She met Rupert while interviewing him
for one of his Australian newspapers.
Anna's on the News Corp board of
directors. She's mother to Elizabeth
James and Lachland and she helped raise
Prudence. As they grow up, Anna worried
about what the competition to succeed
their father was doing to her children.
>> Your sons, are they planning to go into
the newspaper business?
>> I think so, and so is my daughter. I
mean, I can see um lots of arguments
along the way. Who knows what will
happen.
>> It wasn't always easy. Rupert's work
always came first.
>> Newspapers are in his blood. He's a good
Australian businessman who's come here.
I'm going to show you how to do it.
>> And it never ever stopped.
>> It is awful sometimes and it is lonely
and you are cut out of it. I don't think
I change it for anything at all.
For decades, Anna has been patiently
waiting for him to retire so they can
enjoy their golden years together. On
that day, he would name his successor.
Win or lose, the children would all be
free of their burden of succession.
Anna could enjoy life with her husband,
free from the burden of news court
invading every second of their lives.
But instead, in 1998, everything
changed.
By now, Rupert is 67. He still hasn't
retired, and he's met someone else. Her
name is Wendy Deng. She works at one of
Rupert's TV stations in China. She's
been acting as his private translator
when he visits the region, and she's
half his age. Rupert insists nothing is
going on, but Anna is sure he's having
an affair.
Either way, he swiftly cuts Anna out of
his personal and professional lives. At
first, Rupert and Anna announce that
their separation will be amicable. Anna
will remain on the News Corps board, but
then in Newscore's annual report, Anna
reads that she's retiring. Then she
claims he gave her a direct order. You
get off the board.
But Anna has one last card to play.
Legally, she's entitled to have the
assets Rert has created since they've
been married. But she wants something
else. Anna sees what competing for
succession is doing to her children, and
she wants to make sure Rert can never
toss them aside like he has her. To
protect them, she wants to ensure that
all four will inherit a share of the
family business. So, she sacrifices half
of what she's entitled to in the
divorce.
In exchange, Robert agrees to
restructure the family trust. His four
children will each control a single vote
within the trust, while Rert will
control four. But when he dies, his
votes will disappear. Elizabeth, James,
Lachland, and Prudence will control the
trust assets equally. These assets have
been valued at more than 7 billion. But
there's an even bigger prize. They
include almost half of the voting stock
and two of the most influential media
companies in the English-speaking world.
The voting power will also belong to
Rupert's children equally. These
companies decide what millions of people
read, hear, and watch on a daily basis.
[Music]
Managing a huge empire is quite the
challenge. You don't need to be a media
mogul to know that one of the biggest
hassles in any workplace is the chaos of
disconnected tools and software
platforms. But there's a solution. Udu.
Udu is a single centralized platform for
managing your entire business. Need to
track hours, sign documents, manage
projects, or even build a website.
Whatever your needs, Udu has over 45
apps to choose from. What's more,
they're integrated. Thanks to UDO, your
sales, accounting, and inventory
management apps can all update each
other, giving you a cohesive, up-to-date
overview. UDU is even tailored to your
location, so no more wasting time
figuring out local taxes, rates, and
regulations. UDU does it for you. U
grows with you. Start with the apps you
need and add more as your business
evolves. The first application is free
for life with unlimited support and
hosting included. Starting at €19.90 per
month, you gain access to all available
applications. Click the link in the
description to check it out.
In the early 2000s, the Murdoch Empire
was arguably at its peak, reaching five
continents and 3/4 of the world's
population. One of the companies
controlled by the shares in the Murdoch
family trust, NewsCore, owns media
properties all over the world. The other
is the most profitable cable news
channel in America. In time, it'll
become much more. James will later say
that with a trust, the idea was that it
would incentivize us to cooperate. What
actually happens is very different. And
at the heart of it is Fox News.
[Music]
This plane is flying from Sydney to New
York. Inside it, Lachlan Murdoch is
brooding. A few months from now, Lachlan
will describe the events that follow to
a reporter for New York Magazine. Our
description is largely based on that
reporting. Lachlan is now 33 years old.
5 years ago, his father promoted him to
deputy chief operating officer of News
Corp. As deputy COO, Lachlan is
responsible for running the New York
Post, the publisher Harper Collins, and
35 TV stations. Roupert is still head of
the company, and he shows no signs of
slowing down, but he's now 75 years old.
One way or another, he'll have to step
down soon. It's an open secret that
Lachlan is winning the race for
succession. At this point, his sisters
are out of the running, and his brother
James trails behind. Lachlan has long
seemed to have an advantage. He's very
much his father's son, sharing his
conservative politics and deep love for
Australia.
In 1997, Rert told an interviewer that
of his children, Lachlan was first among
equals.
But something isn't right. Lately, he's
in conflict with Audrey Als, the father
of Fox News. As one of Rupert's most
trusted executives, Ills is largely
allowed to do what he likes. This
includes pushing his ideas for the TV
stations Lachlan is in charge of most
recent idea is a show called Crimeline.
For financial reasons, Lachland turned
it down. According to New York magazine,
Als went to Rupert and told him about
Crimeline. Rupert told him, "Do the
show. Don't listen to Lachlan.
Lachlan feels undermined by Rupert and
it isn't the first time. Now he's
heading back to America. He and his
father are going to have a talk.
In New York, Lachlan and Rupert discuss
the situation over lunch. Rupert
listens. He offers suggestions. Maybe
changing the organization chart. But
Lachlan knows his father isn't going to
change. He wouldn't ask him to. Still,
if things stay as they are, their
relationship could seriously
deteriorate.
Something begins to dawn on Lachlan.
He's used to thinking about himself in
relation to the company and to his
father. It's just difficult to sort of
uncouple your life and your identity
from the company, he thinks. Then he
makes the decision. I have to do my own
thing, he says. I have to be my own man.
And with that, he steps down as deputy
COO and moves back to Australia with his
family. He remains on the newspore
board. But in the race for succession,
he's no longer the leader.
Suddenly, James is.
By this time, James is a long way from
his years as a rebel. Back in 1995, he
co-founded the hip-hop label Rockus
Records. But then, Roert bought the
label, dragging his son into the family
business. He's been busy proving himself
ever since. In 2007, he receives a major
promotion to running Newscore operations
through Europe and Asia. Then, something
strange happens. James personality
reportedly seems to change. He'd always
been energetic, analytical, offbeat. At
work, he was known as technocratic and
given to business jargon, but now he
seems brash, cocky. Some think he's
emulating his father, and he's
reportedly assembled a loyal team in
London. To many, it looks like a rival
power center in the company. No one
knows exactly how Rert sees this, but to
some observers, he seems proud and maybe
a bit threatened.
In 2010, Rupert proposes something
unusual. family therapy. At a retreat at
the Murdoch family in Caven Station,
Australia, a specialist will help him
and his adult children work on how they
treat each other. Months later, news of
the retreat was leaked to Vanity Fair.
The magazine describes how the siblings
came together to help James become a
better leader and improve his
relationship with Rupert. James later
described something very different to
The Atlantic. According to him, the
therapist first met with everyone
individually. Then at a session with the
whole family, everything supposedly fell
apart. According to James, there was
gaslighting, accusations, strategic
maneuvering. Even in family therapy,
each of the Murdochs were advancing a
personal agenda. James describes it as a
car crash that left the family in even
worse shape. Afterward, Elizabeth
supposedly offers to create a family
constitution. According to The Atlantic,
James helps her. Together they create a
draft including principles like we
commit to undertake active dialogue with
each other at all times and to
relentlessly communicate openly with
trust and humility and we will be
vigilant of and defend against
divisiveness either between us or that
which could infiltrate from without. In
February 2011, Elizabeth, James,
Lachland, and Prudence reportedly all
signed the document. But their newfound
resolve to stick together is about to be
tested like never before.
This is Rupert Murdoch's war room.
Rupert is fighting to contain the
biggest scandal in Newscore history.
Elizabeth is advising him and also
providing emotional support. According
to reporting, she thinks the best public
relations move would be to let someone
in the family take the fall. And her
brother James is in charge of newspore
operations in Europe and Asia. It should
be him.
Rupert slept on the idea. He agrees.
Then he sends Elizabeth down the hall to
fire her brother.
From 1996 to 2001, Elizabeth was
managing director of the British
satellite TV network B SkyB, which later
changed his name to Sky. She worked hard
to position herself as Rupert's
successor. Then in 2000, she abruptly
quit. In one version of the story, she
let Rupert know by sending him a fax.
The exact reason is unknown, but many
believe that within the family,
Elizabeth had long been hitting the
glass ceiling. Years later, James would
reportedly save Rupert. He is a
misogynist.
After quitting the family business,
Elizabeth was successful on her own
terms in a way none of her siblings had
been. Her production company, Shine,
produced hit TV shows like The Biggest
Loser and Master Chef.
In early 2011, Rert bought Shine for 673
million, bringing Elizabeth back into
the fold. He also asked her to join the
News Corps board. She said yes, but
quickly changed her mind, perhaps to
distance herself from the massive
scandal erupting around Newsore.
On July 4th, 2011, an article in the
Guardian blew the lid of a long
simmering scandal. Reporters from
Rupert's beloved tabloid, News of the
World, had allegedly been hacking the
phones of people they reported on.
According to the Guardian, this included
Millie Dollar, a teenager who had been
abducted and murdered back in 2002. The
scandal snowballed. The victims of phone
hacking were said to include deceased
soldiers, people killed in the London
bombing in 2005, and a huge parade of
celebrities, even the royal family. This
had all happened before James took over
as CEO. But he was linked to the scandal
nonetheless, and he scrambled to contain
the damage. His efforts reportedly
included firings, internal changes, and
a PR campaign.
>> Practices of certain individuals did not
live up to the standards and quality of
journalism that we believe in and that I
believe in. and that this company
believes in.
>> But then Rupert came to London and
things got worse. He spoke to reporters.
He met with the parents of Millie
Dollar, the murdered teenager. None of
this was coordinated with James. Rupert
seemed to be undermining his son and CEO
at every turn. Testifying before
parliamentary committee, he continued to
act on his own repeatedly. It even
looked like he was throwing James under
the bus.
>> As for my comments, Mr. chairman of my
statement which I believe was around the
closure uh of the News of the World
newspaper.
>> Before you get to that, I would just
like to say one sentence.
>> This is the most humble day of my life.
>> Thank you.
>> That is the first I've heard of that.
>> Elizabeth follows her instructions and
walks down to James' office. She tells
him that both she and her father think
he should step down. Years later, James
will describe his feelings in extended
interviews with The Atlantic. He's
stunned at Rupert's cowardice. He tells
Elizabeth to make their father do the
dirty work himself. Elizabeth and James'
relationship will never be the same. For
years, the two siblings will barely
speak. Elizabeth will eventually call
the episode one of her life's biggest
regrets.
James denies knowing the phone hacking
had been a widespread problem, but his
own employees claim under oath that they
told him about it. The parliamentary
committee concludes that at minimum,
James has shown an astonishing lack of
curiosity. The scandal forces Rert to
shut down News of the World, the tabloid
that established him in the UK. To
contain the fallout, he also splits his
empire in two. Print media remains part
of a reconstituted News Corp. While
television and film become 21st Century
Fox. James takes most of the blame for
the scandal. Rert relocates him to New
York where he's made deputy chief
operating officer of News Corp. It's
spun as a promotion, but James was
running operations in Europe and Asia
completely on his own. In New York, he
reports to the COO
He's back under his father's watchful
eye.
Four years pass. Rupert is now 83 years
old and he's still the head of his
companies.
It's lunchtime in the corporate dining
room at Fox News headquarters. Rupert
Murdoch is having lunch with Jared
Kushner, Ivanka Trump, and her father.
Right as their food hits the table,
Donald Trump shares his big news. He's
running for president.
Rupert's eyes reportedly stay on his
soup. He says only that Trump will have
to be ready to take some hits in the
press. The two men have known each other
a long time going all the way back to
New York in the 70s and 80s. Roupert is
close friends with Jared Kushner.
They've even vacationed together.
Roupert is politically conservative and
in 2011 Fox News was the platform for
Trump's false birther crusade in which
he repeatedly claimed that President
Barack Obama lacked an American birth
certificate. But according to an
unconfirmed account by author Michael
Wolf, who has interviewed Rupert
extensively, Rupert supposedly considers
Donald Trump quote, "a [__] idiot."
When the time comes for the first
Republican primary debate, New York
Magazine claims he instructs the
moderator, Megan Kelly, to make things
hard for Trump.
>> You've called women you don't like fat
pigs, dogs, slobs, and disgusting
animals.
>> But when Fox hosts continue to support
other candidates and mock Trump, he
skips the channel second debate. Trump's
base and Fox's core audience are largely
the same people. Without him, the second
debate on Fox gets about half as many
viewers. Trump may be a [__] idiot in
Rupert's mind, but he seems to be
crucial to Fox's ratings. The question
is, can Rupert afford not to back him?
It's a major turning point for Fox News.
As the 2016 Republican presidential
primaries wind down, Trump was starting
to look inevitable. By now, the support
of the Murdoch media had become crucial
to Republican candidates.
But Trump flipped this around thanks to
social media. He had his own loyal
audience. If Fox didn't support him,
they might just go somewhere else.
Thanks to alternatives like Breitbart
and One American News, Fox was no longer
the only conservative media outlet in
town. So Rupert seemingly pivoted.
ProTrump articles began popping up in
the editorial section of the Wall Street
Journal, a Murdoch paper. The covers of
the New York Post began celebrating
Trump's politically incorrect stances.
And Fox News featured hours of proTrump
programming in its prime time lineup. At
Fox, Trump was now the guy. According to
at least one Fox anchor, the new rule
was don't bash him. The anchor is quoted
saying, "We've thrown in the towel."
In November 2016, Trump won the
presidency of the United States.
>> Right away, Rert begins visiting the
White House. He's frequently on the
phone with the new president, sometimes
weekly. It's the culmination of Rupert's
outsized ambition. He's come a long way
from his secret lunch with Margaret
Thatcher. He now has a direct line to
the White House. Over the phone, Trump
reportedly says to him, "Rupert, Rupert,
you love this shit."
>> Soon, Fox's lineup changes. It seems
more closely aligned with Trump's
politics with proTrump personalities
like Tucker Carlson and Sean Hannity
filling prime time slots. Trump often
gets up early and watches Fox, then
seemingly tweets about what he's seen.
Commenters begin to notice a feedback
loop developing. Some note that at times
it's hard to tell where policy positions
come from. Trump or Fox. There was a
time when Fox drove Republican politics.
Now it's becoming something totally new.
A TV network that to many looks
inseparable from the White House. Fox is
arguably more powerful than ever. And
it's still unclear who will follow in
Rupert's footsteps.
More than a year earlier, this is the
Lamb's Club in Midtown Manhattan. James
Murdoch is flying to Indonesia today,
but he's made time for lunch with
Lachlan and the COO of News Corp before
he heads to the airport. Years from now,
he'll discuss the events that follow in
his interview with The Atlantic. James
is 42. It's been 4 years since the phone
hacking scandal, and its effects are
still being felt. Still, the succession
race may be coming to an end. When the
time comes, reports say James will be
the CEO of 21st Century Fox. Lachlan
will be given a ceremonial title.
But then something unexpected happens.
Lachlan breaks the news. He's returning
to the US to run 21st Century Fox.
Lachlan, who quit years ago and hid in
Australia while James toiled in the
company and took the blame when things
went wrong.
Lachlan is going to be his boss.
At this point, James has been in the
family business for almost 20 years.
He's paid his dues, but behind his back,
his father's been making plans for his
brother to return. In fact, he'd never
fully given up on bringing his favorite
son back.
>> I hope and have said from the day he
went back there that he's going to come
back here.
>> James does not want to report to his
brother. He gets up and heads to the
airport. While he's gone, he ignores
messages from Rert and Lachlan. Rumors
about him resigning whip through the
company. By the time he returns, Rupert
has changed his tune. James will still
become CEO. Lachlan will be chairman. In
reality, he sets his sons up as
co-leaders. Both are expected to sign
off on every major decision, but
according to several accounts, the
arrangement is a disaster. The brothers
are unable to work together. In the fall
of 2018, James spots a way out. A deal
is beginning to take shape. Disney will
buy nearly all of 21st Century Fox's
assets, but not Fox News. James is
enthusiastic. The deal could give him
cover for exiting the company. Lachlan,
on the other hand, is reportedly
enraged. He's relocated his family from
Australia to be head of a top tier media
property and his father wants to sell it
out from under him. In his interview
with The Atlantic, James describes
events coming to a head. Over dinner at
the Grand Mercy Tavern in New York,
Lachlan blows up. He rants about the
deal, makes threats, and finally storms
out. On the way out, he tells Roert that
if the deal goes through, you will not
have a son. Then he looks at James and
you won't have a brother.
But less than a year later, it happens.
Disney buys 21st Century Fox. Rupert's
children receive an enormous payout from
the family trust, about $2 billion each.
James steps down as CEO of 21st Century
Fox, and exits the family business.
Lachlan becomes chief executive of Fox,
and along with Rupert, co-executive
chairman of Fox and News Corp. The
father and his favorite son are left
running the Family Pistons together,
just as Rupert always dreamed. The fight
for succession seems to finally be over,
but the real battle is about to begin.
[Music]
November 3rd, 2020. Election night,
Trump versus Biden. Americans are glued
to their screens. One by one, voting
ends in each state. Millions of ballots
are counted, and projections begin to
take shape for the winner in each of the
50 states. Those projections are
influential. They can shape public
perception of who's going to win.
>> Just before 11:20 p.m. Eastern time, Fox
News makes a bold call.
>> He's calling Arizona for Joe Biden. That
is a big get.
>> It's a risky move. Arizona is a hotly
contested state in the presidential
election, and data is still coming in,
but being first to call the state could
be a journalistic coup for Fox. It's
only prudent for the election desk to
get approval before taking such a risky
move. Much later, a Murdoch biographer
describes the decision this way. The Fox
higher-ups sign up on a call one by one.
The decision eventually reaches Lachlan,
then Rupert. Will you approve announcing
such a huge loss for Trump?
>> [__] him,
>> Rupert reportedly says. Fox made the
projection. The Trump team is furious.
They barrage Fox with demands the call
be reversed. Fox refuses, but it seems
Fox's audience is also furious. In the
days that follow, ratings plummet. Then
Fox pivots.
>> Tonight, every American should be angry.
You should be outraged. You should be
worried. You should be concerned at what
has happened in the election.
>> The Dominion software system has been
tagged as one allegedly capable of
flipping votes. How, for example, did
scenile hermit Joe Biden get 15 million
more votes than his former boss,
rockstar crowd surfer Barack Obama? It
gets behind Trump's false narrative
about the election being stolen. None of
the higherups at Fox seem to believe
those claims. Rupert reportedly calls
them really crazy stuff. Still, internal
communications show that many inside the
network believe that Fox needs to get
back in its audience's good graces to
recover in the ratings. It's possible
that echoing whatever Trump says will do
that, but that will both cost Fox and
the Murdoch family dearly. After Fox
promotes the Stop the Steel narrative,
Dominion Voting Systems, a voting
machine company, sues the network for
defamation. Fox settles out of court for
almost $800 million.
The Murdoch Empire skews politically
conservative, but the Murdoch children
seem to vary. As Fox News transforms
under Trump, experts say their political
differences become more stark. Lachlan
has long been known as conservative. But
according to his brother James,
something changes. He now seems more
partisan and reactionary, even willing
to consider farright ideas like white
nativism.
Commentators have long seen Elizabeth
and Pru as more liberal than the rest of
the family. They've never said so
publicly, but as the family business
drifts rightward, private communications
obtained by journalists seem to indicate
a willingness to push back against
positions like climate change denial.
James' politics have always been harder
to pin down. But just before leaving the
family business, he begins to give hints
of where he stands. Back in 2017,
neo-Nazis marched in Charlottesville,
Virginia. They carried torches enchanted
blood and soil, and Jews will not
replace us. There are violent and even
deadly clashes with counterprotesters
and police. When asked about the events,
Trump seems to partially defend the
neo-Nazis. You had some very bad people
in that group, but you also had people
that were
very fine people on both sides.
>> In fairness, this was taken out of
context at the time. He's talking about
other protesters who were supposedly at
this rally. In the same speech, Trump
explicitly condemns neo-Nazis and white
nationalists. In any case, Fox News
defended him.
>> I think the president made a strong and
clear message condemning all hate
groups.
>> James was disgusted. As CEO, he wanted
to release a statement to his employees
making his position clear. But he
couldn't face the push back he assumed
he'd get from Lachlan and their father.
But his feelings became clear when an
email he wrote to colleagues was leaked
to the press. In it, he wrote, "I can't
even believe I have to write this.
Standing up to Nazis is essential. There
are no good Nazis." James saw this as a
nonpartisan matter. He didn't
necessarily mind catering to
conservative viewers. He did want to at
least nudge the company towards
accountability and higher editorial
standards, but he believed Rert would
never allow him to change the company's
direction or decouple it from Trump.
The battle for succession seemed
resolved. It was Lachlan, but all four
siblings still had a vote on the family
trust that made their opinions on Fox's
political orientations especially
relevant. If James, Elizabeth, and
Prudence decided to change Fox's
direction, all they had to do was wait
for Roert to pass away. At that point,
they would outvote Lachlan. That very
prospect would ignite the Murdoch
family's final battle.
[Music]
It's 2020. This is Australia's black
summer. Bushfire season has raged out of
control, reducing 19 million hectares of
land and 3,000 homes to ash. 33 people
are dead. Most consider the cause to be
at least partially due to climate
change, but not the Murdoch properties.
They call it arson.
>> So, let me deal with the issue head on.
Does climate change cause these fires?
No.
>> So, that's the key, the drought. And if
the drought can't be blamed on climate
change, you can't blame the fires on
climate change, especially when so many
are deliberately lit.
>> James is still on the News Corps board,
but in January, he releases a statement.
He and his wife don't just believe in
climate change. They're particularly
disappointed with the ongoing denial
among the news outlets in Australia
given obvious evidence to the contrary.
According to James, the rest of the
board is so angry that he's pressured to
resign. And he does, cutting his last
remaining tie to the family business.
Except for the trust.
Speculation runs rampant. The media
begins to report a rift in the family.
Some ask if James is willing to
contradict the company's climate change
deniialism. What will he do when Rupert
dies? Will he try to drag the family
business towards the political center?
According to The Atlantic, around this
time, James' wife, Catherine, saw a kind
of conspiracy theory begin to take hold
between Rert and Lachlan. Rert had
always been known as conservative, but
not particularly partisan. His
newspapers had supported Thatcher and
Reagan, but also the center-left British
Prime Minister Tony Blair. In 2008, he
and the rest of the family were even
have said to have backed Obama. But some
believe that in the Trump era, he had
grown more partisan. If this was true,
and if James, Elizabeth, and Pru were
planning to drag the network to the left
when he died, that made them a threat.
This growing mistrust between the
Murdochs sent them on the road to the
courtroom in Nevada. The trial that
followed would be held in secret. But in
2025, two New York Times reporters
obtained nearly the entire record of the
trial, including a huge number of
private messages between the Murdochs
that were introduced as evidence. The
direct quotes that follow are based on
that reporting. According to the Times,
after the Disney deal, Lachlan
repeatedly tried to buy his siblings out
of their shares of the trust and cement
his own control. His attempts failed.
During the Black Summer, Rupert sent him
a message of encouragement. Been
thinking a lot overnight about the deal
with James at all. benefit of getting
him out probably outweighs other
considerations.
Around this time, some observers believe
Elizabeth, James, and Prudence were
becoming a united front. When Rupert
died, they would sort things out. With
three votes on the trust, they could
afford to wait.
Soon, they would realize just how
unprepared they were.
It's April 9th, 2023. Succession is
playing on HBO. The show is based on the
Murdoch. The series is now in its fourth
season. The main character, family
patriarch Logan Roy, is modeled on
Rupert. So far, the show has been
heavily based on real life Murdoch lore.
But in this episode, the show diverges
sharply. Attention, major spoilers
ahead. Skip until here if you want to
avoid them.
>> It is very, very bad.
>> It seems very bad. I'm so sorry to call
you like this.
>> Can you put him on?
>> Suddenly, and unexpectedly, Logan Roy
dies, but it happens offcreen. The
viewer experiences Logan's death through
the reaction of his children who find
out via a phone call. According to the
New York Times, Elizabeth Murdoch is
watching, and she feels panic rising
inside her. Logan Royce children are
completely unprepared. No one is in
charge. Chaos reigns and eventually they
lose control of the company. It all hits
way too close to home. Elizabeth's
father is now old, very old, 92. In
2018, he tripped and fell while on
Lachland's yacht, suffering
life-threatening injuries. In 2022, he
was hospitalized with CO. Someday soon,
it will just be Elizabeth, James,
Lachland, and Prudence running the
family's trust. The fate of the Murdoch
companies will be in their hands. But
can they work together? Elizabeth is
deeply shaken. So is Mark Dero, her
representative on the family trust. He
sees the episode as a grim warning. I
thought this is exactly exactly the
thing we should be avoiding because that
is chaotic. So Devou writes what he
calls the succession memo. In it, he
poses questions intended to prepare
Elizabeth, James, and Prudence for
what's to come. When they have equal say
in the direction of the empire, could
James accept Fox News as it is? If not,
can someone buy him out? On the other
hand, if he and Elizabeth and Prudence
want to move Fox News to the center,
would Lachlan accept it? But Rupert is
still very much alive, and he's making
plans to stop this very thing.
[Music]
It's early December 2023. Rupert is here
to speak to his daughters. A few months
ago, he finally retired. He retains only
a ceremonial title, Emirus, chairman of
the Fox board, but he still controls the
trust, and he's about to make big
changes. He's called a special meeting
of the trust board. It's in 2 days.
Before he pulls the trigger, he wants to
see where Elizabeth and Prudence stand.
At 4 p.m. he meets with Prudence. Rupert
has talking points prepared. These
companies are my legacy. I put
everything into them over my life. The
Murdoch companies are protector of the
conservative voice in the
English-speaking world. Then he comes
out with it. I love each of my children
and my support of Lachlan is not
intended to suggest otherwise. But these
companies need a designated leader and
Lachlan is that leader.
Gradually, Rupert reveals his plan. He,
Lachlan, and a team of lawyers and
executives have been working on it in
secret for months. They call it Project
Family Harmony.
According to reporting by the New York
Times, the Murdoch family trust is
controlled by a single entity called
Crudin Financial Services. Crudin is run
by six managing directors, Elizabeth,
James, Lachlan, and Prudence. Each one
have a managing director with a single
vote. Roupert has two directors with two
votes. Rupert can never be outvoted, but
when he dies, his votes will disappear.
His four children will control the trust
equally. So the plan is to create two
new trustees, Crudin 2 and Crudin 3.
Rert would control one, Lachlan the
other. When Rupert dies, control of both
would pass the Lachlan. Lachlan would
have more power over the trust than even
Rert ever had. Even working together,
James, Elizabeth, and Prudence would be
completely disenfranchised.
But there is a catch. Legally, Rupert
couldn't change the trust unless his
changes were in good faith and in the
best interest of the beneficiaries they
affected.
So, the argument is this. James,
Elizabeth, and Prudence are planning to
change the political orientation of Fox
News. If they did that, ratings would
drop, shares would become less
profitable, and the trust would suffer.
With Lachlan in total control, Fox would
remain profitable, benefiting everyone.
When her father is finished, Prudence is
lost for words. All she can manage is
right. Later he explains the plan to
Elizabeth. Her response is more
straightforward. You are completely
disenfranchising me and my siblings.
You've blown a hole in the family.
Rupert leaves London without either
daughter's support. Later, Elizabeth
texted Lachlan that Project Family
harmony was a massive gut punch. Lachlan
wrote back, "Hey Liz, I really
appreciate your support. Today is about
dad's wishes and confirming all of our
support for him and for his wishes. It
shouldn't be difficult or controversial.
Love you, Lachlan. The special meeting
happened over Zoom. Roert read out the
changes from a prepared script. The next
day, he formally filed the changes to
the trust. Later on, details would
emerge that suggested the changes had a
single target, James. In Project Family
Harmony documents, he was called a
troublesome beneficiary or just
troublesome. The real goal was to stop
him at all costs. Later, Rupert sent
James a copy of his script from the Zoom
call. A note said, "James, still time to
talk. Love, Dad. P.S. love to see my
grandchildren one day." Ironically, with
these changes, Rupert has started the
very rebellion he was trying to avoid.
It's September 16th, 2024.
Wu County Courthouse. Immediately after
Rupert filed the changes to the trust,
Elizabeth, James, and Prudence formally
objected. They're inside these SUVs.
Half an hour later, the second wave with
Rupert and Lachlan arrives. Today is
their first day in court. The
descriptions that follow are based on
records of the trial obtained by the New
York Times.
Rupert is the first in the family to
take the stand. He's 93. His voice is
sometimes faint, but he still seems
perfectly lucid. He's asked about his
motivation in changing the trust. He
says, "If there's uncertainty about the
management, the public will feel it
inside. The company would feel it."
Ensuring Lachland succession will
eliminate this uncertainty once and for
all, everyone will know where they
stand. I just felt sure, very certain,
that if these things weren't settled,
there would be trouble, and the trouble
would be damaging. The opposition
lawyers question him. Isn't Project
Family Harmony really about preserving
Rupert's legacy by keeping Fox News on
the political right? Rupert tells him
there's no difference between the two.
If Fox changes its political
orientation, its audience will rebel
again. Lachlan will keep things as they
are, ensuring that the network and that
the family's trust shares remain
valuable. That benefits the whole
family. His whole case rests on this
argument. The changes are only intended
to benefit shareholders. But then he
keeps going. Fox News cannot fall into
the wrong hands. It will be a disaster
if it does. And the one at fault is
James. Because of him, Elizabeth and
Prudence will have to choose between
their brothers. if one day they all
share control over the trust.
After his testimony, Rupert is excused
from court due to illness. But James
suspects another reason, cowardice.
On day three, Elizabeth takes the stand.
Rupert's lawyer paints her, Prudence,
and James as spoiled billionaire
children determined to thwart the man
who had made them wealthy beyond most
people's wildest dreams. Hasn't
Elizabeth been fortunate to have become
a multi-billionaire thanks to her
father's enormous generosity? Elizabeth
replies, I wouldn't call it generosity,
but his enormous success. Yes. She is
grateful to her father, though. All her
life, he had mentored her in media and
business. I feel like I was taught at
the feet of the master. The lawyer hones
in on a meeting that took place a year
before. James, Elizabeth, Prudence, and
their spouses had all met for dinner at
Clarages, a London hotel and restaurant.
Beforehand, the siblings had met in a
private conference room for 90 minutes.
They caught up, talked about the
succession memo and plans for Rupert's
death and complained about Lachlan and
their family. Or so they said.
Before the trial, a piece of evidence
had come to light. In his diary,
Prudence's representative to the trust
had written about the brother's
activities and the meeting at Clarages.
In it, he writes that the three are
planning to get rid of Lachlan. Rupert's
lawyers paint a picture of a full-blown
conspiracy. Elizabeth's lawyer develops
a competing image. Rupert and Lachlan
are the ones who've been scheming. It's
Project Family Harmony that has torn the
family in two, not some supposed
conspiracy by Elizabeth, James, and
Prudence. He asks Elizabeth to describe
how Rupert explained his plans to her.
She describes feeling angry and
betrayed. "What is your relationship
with your father like today?" the lawyer
asks. "Absent, "What was it like before
the December 6th special meeting?"
"Unbelievably close.
In the afternoon on day three, James
testifies. Rupert's lawyers seek to
portray him as a resentful son plotting
his revenge. A puppet master scheming to
undermine his brother. James admits they
talked about outvoting Lachlan when
their father died, but he insists they
never discussed a coup. The lawyer asks
about the dinner where Lachlan had
essentially disowned him because of the
Disney deal, and James is surprised to
find himself crying. Later on, he chokes
up when discussing his relationship with
his father. You know, there have been a
lot of hurtful things over the years. He
tells the court, "We worked together
very closely for a long time. It's
hard." But he's direct when asked about
identifying as the troublesome
beneficiary. He calls the label garbage.
They're making stuff up or believing
things that are being told to create
some sort of boogeyman that is a
justification for stealing stuff they
didn't want to buy.
Day four, Lachlan is called to the
stand.
A question hangs over the trial. Is he
the target of a plot by his siblings or
is he targeting them? He insists that
evidence of a plot against him has been
piling up for years. He says thousands
of stories in the media have quoted
anonymous sources close to James,
confirming his plans to ou Lachlan. One
unauthorized biography of Lachlan quotes
an anonymous source. Lachlan gets fired
the day Rupert dies. As Lachlan sees it,
quotes like this clearly come from
people close to James. Taken together,
they show why Lachlan and Rert had to
act. But under cross-examination, cracks
begin to appear. Lachlan can't approve
that the anonymous sources come from
James. In fact, he's changed his mind.
Now he thinks they're people close to
Elizabeth. But it's revealed that the
source of the biography quote is much
closer to home. It's a friend and
adviser of Lachlan's who spoke to the
author for more than 14 hours, and
Lachlan had approved it. At least some
of his evidence of a plot had come from
within his own camp. Lachlan is forced
to walk back other things, too. And he
admits that changing the trust wasn't
Rupert's idea. It was his.
[Music]
On December 7th, the probate court
commissioner filed his report. It was
unambiguous, even harsh. Rupert and
Lachlan had acted in bad faith. Item by
item, he dismissed the supposed evidence
of a sibling plot. The Clarage's meeting
had amounted to no more than a casual
and inco conversation. Lachlan's
testimony had been misleading.
Statements he had made about a failed
corporate merger were an example of
Lachland Murdoch's lack of cander with
the parties and on the witness stand.
Ultimately, the changes to the trust
were a carefully crafted charade. Their
motivation was political. To ensure that
Rupert's companies continue to be
alternative conservative voices in media
after he dies, Roert and Lachlan
immediately appealed. According to the
New York Times, their chances of success
were slim. James, Elizabeth, and
Prudence intentions remained unknown.
Time seemed to be on their side, though.
When Robert died, they would have the
power to reorient the Murdoch companies.
Behind the scenes, things may not have
been so cut and dried. According to the
reporting by the New York Times in
February 2025, the balance of power
seemed to shift. Rupert and Lachlan's
appeal nudged forward with a state judge
requesting oral arguments, and The
Atlantic published a profile of James.
In it, he criticized his father and
brother and shared sensitive details of
the sealed court case. Rupert and
Lachlland's lawyers pounced, requesting
sanctions against James, and a whole new
trial. Outside of the trial, Rupert
seemed more powerful than ever in some
ways. Trump is once again president.
Former Fox employees pepper the
administration, including Trump's
cabinet. Roupert has resumed his visits
to the White House, though his
relationship with Trump isn't without
turbulence. In July 2025, Trump even
sued Rupert in his paper, the Wall
Street Journal, for its claims about a
body note he allegedly wrote to Jeffrey
Epstein.
As the appeal seemed to progress, the
Murdoch headed back to the negotiating
table. In September 2025, a deal was
announced. Elizabeth, James, and
Prudence would sell their shares of
their empire for $1.1 billion each. The
current Murdoch family trust will be
dissolved and a new one created,
including Lachlan and Rupert's two
daughters with Wendy Deng, Grace, and
Kloe. In a way, both sides could claim
victory. Elizabeth, James, and Prudence
were finally severing their ties with an
empire they increasingly seem to
disagree with politically and doing so
with an impressive payout. Lachland
would succeed his father as head of the
family business, and Rupert, after
decades of intrigue and infighting, has
finally secured his legacy. In Lachlan's
hands, Fox News and News Corp, seem
likely to stay reliably conservative.
They will remain what Rupert has always
envisioned, a family business. But the
family itself may never be the same.